Inventory of the Mills E. Godwin Jr. Papers 1947-1989
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Scrapbooks, 1943-1978., 40 Scrapbooks. (Box 1-21)
  - Second Term As Governor, July 1, 1976-December 31. (Box-folder 19:37)
  - Southern Governors' Conference and Presidential Campaign, 1976. (Box-folder 20:38)
  - Second Term As Governor, January 1, 1977-June 30, 1977. (Box-folder 20:39)
  - Scrapbook pertaining to Mills E. Godwin, Jr., July 1, 1977-January, 1978. (Box-folder 21:40)
  Series 9: Political Memorabilia and Selected Material
- Political Memorabilia and Selected Material, 1965-1973. (Box-folder 27)
  This series consists of one large box of 1973 campaign material, of which two binders have been placed on microfilm, and one small box which contains magazines, news clippings, and small scrapbooks concerning special activities. One envelope of unclassified photographs and copies of inaugural programs and invitations for 1966 and 1974 are also included.
  Other items in this series include VEA Convention edition - Godwin, Virginia's Education Governor, 1973. Papers: Virginia's Future First; Howell Rejects; 88%; Yes, Godwin stands for Neighborhood Schools; Yes, Godwin will protect our Right to Work Law; And Where Does Henry's Money Come From; Henry's Tax Scheme, Can You Afford It; Virginia's Future, Let's Give it Our Best; On the One Hand, But on the Other, Let's Keep Henry Honest. Godwin bumper stickers and buttons. Virginia Record, July, 1973, Mills E. Godwin, Jr., The Man for Virginia; The New Majority Program. Posters: Mills Godwin, The Clearest Choice for Virginia's Future; Virginia's Future, Give it Your Best - Godwin for Governor; Dalton for Lieutenant-Governor. Godwin for Governor stationery; Godwin for Governor buttons; Volunteer Register, September 4-November 2, 1973. Black notebook containing congratulatory letters and thank you letters sent to lists in notebook; blue notebook containing sample letters sent to groups and individuals for support and help in Godwin's inauguration.
  The items listed separately below are those that have been microfilmed.
  - Letter from Peggy Miller, Williamsburg, to Mrs. Mills E. Godwin, Jr., with illustration for proposed inaugural ball gown enclosed, November 1, 1973., Microfilmed. (Box-folder 27:1)
  - "The Night Before Christmas" by Walter S. Griggs, Jr., n.d., Microfilmed. (Box-folder 27:2)
  - Nominating speech of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., for President of the United States, along with note explaining why speech was not delivered, 1968., Microfilmed. (Box-folder 27:3)
  - Circus Saints and Sinners Script, 1966., Microfilmed. (Box-folder 27:4)
  - Report on the European Trade Mission, May 1969., Microfilmed. (Box-folder 27:5)
  - List of campaign contributions, 1965., Microfilmed. (Box-folder 27:6)
  - Daily list of campaign contributions, 1965., Microfilmed. (Box-folder 27:7)
  - List of campaign managers, 1965., Microfilmed. (Box-folder 27:8)
  - Letter from Jim Moore, Charlottesville, to "Bud", with congratulations on victory, November 8, 1965., Microfilmed. (Box-folder 27:9)
  Series 10: Accession 1985.15
- Accession 1985.15, 1978-1983., 3 boxes. (Box 28-30)
  These papers of Mills E. Godwin begin after he left gubernatorial office in 1978. Godwin remained a significant player in Virginia political circles, hoping to maintain the power of the coalition of conservative Democrats and Republicans which he headed. The papers concern the U. S. Senate campaigns of 1978 (Warner v. ), and 1982, the gubernatorial campaign of 1981 (Robb v. Coleman), investment policies of Virginia, affirmative action (quotas), public employee collective bargaining, Virginia Wesleyan College, Harry F. Byrd, Jr.'s decision to retire from the Senate, the Martin Luther King holiday in Virginia (federal and state), Republican Party of Virginia, General Assembly and local elections, the Virginia Community College System and the city of Suffolk.
  Correspondents include Gerald Baliles, Harry F. Byrd, Jr., J. Marshall Coleman, John N. Dalton, Gerald R. Ford, Albertis Harrison, Charles S. Robb, D. French Slaughter, and John Warner. There are also routine letters written by Godwin of sympathy, get-well wishes, recommendation as well as replies to requests for help.
  This addition continues with the box numbers of the larger collection that ended with Series 9. The series is arranged primarily by date.
  - General Papers, 1961-1975. (Box 28)
    These items include newspaper clippings (1961 and 1965), letters upon his election as lieutenant-governor in 1961, lists of guests to be invited to inauguration and inaugural programs of 1965 and 1974.
  - General Papers, 1978. (Box 28)
    These items include letters of sympathy, get-well letters, congratulations on retirements, help with problems, requests for contributions to various organizations, etc. Correspondents include: Albertis Harrison concerning the U. S. Senate campaign (Warner); Harry F. Byrd, Jr. concerning the city of Suffolk HUD grant; Gerald Baliles; William E. Simon; D. French Slaughter; James R Thompson (governor of Illinois); and Carter Olin Lowance.
  - Governor's Office Papers, 1978. (Box 28)
    These items include material from or about John N. Dalton (investment policies of Virginia [series of articles by David Chandler in Norfolk Ledger-Star], Division of Purchases and Supply, Warner nomination for Senate), Carter Lowance, Charles S. Robb (Virginia Forum on Education), John N. Dalton, Virginia Port Authority), Louis R. Lawson (Virginia Energy Office), Stanley C. Walker (Virginia State Crime Commission), Virginia Foundation for Independent Colleges, affirmative action (quotas), letters of commendation, and policy statement on public employer-employee relations (collective bargaining).
  - Political Papers, 1978-1979. (Box 28)
    These items include material from or about Wyatt B. Durrette, Jr., Charles S. Robb (lieutenant-governor), Hunter Andrews, Eva F. Scott (first woman to serve in State Senate), A. L. Philpott, Herbert H. Bateman, Paul Trible, General Assembly elections of 1979, J. Marshall Coleman, Philip Crane, Republican senatorial primary of 1978 (Linwood Holton, Richard Obenshain, John Warner, Nathan Miller), agreement of Virginia with HEW to institute quotas in colleges; and the campaign by Coleman for attorney-general in 1977.
  - Republican Party Papers, 1978-1981. (Box 28)
    These items include material from or about the U. S Senate election of 1982, the General Assembly election of 1981, the gubernatorial race of 1981, Byrd's decision to retire from U S. Senate, Herbert H. Bateman, Republican Party events, Wyatt B. Durrette, Martin Luther King holiday bill (state holiday), Paul Trible, coalition headed by Godwin described in newspaper article ( Roanoke Times and World News(November 15, 1980), Eva F. Scott (first woman to serve in State Senate), John Warner, Bob Dole, and the Richard D. Obenshain Republican Center.
  - Virginia State Chamber of Commerce Education Committee, 1978-1981. (Box 28)
  - Virginia Wesleyan College, 1978-1984. (Box 28)
    Godwin's service as a member of the Board of Trustees, and as Honorary Chairman of Challenge of the 80's, decade-long campaign to raise money launched in 1980.
  - Personal and Business Papers, 1978-1979. (Box 28)
    Items include material from or about Gerald R. Ford.
  - Newspaper Clippings and Photographs, 1978-1984. (Box 28)
    Items all concern Godwin.
  - General Papers, 1979. (Box 29)
    Items include letters of sympathy, requests for help, requests for photographs. Items also include material from or about the Richard Obenshain Republican Center; Harry F. Byrd, Jr., concerning Colgate Darden; Richard Poff; Virginia Community College System; and the Eastern Virginia Medical School, concerning in vitro fertilization.
  - Connally for President, 1979-1980. (Box 29)
    Godwin served as the state chair for this committee. Also includes letters from Connally.
  - General Papers, 1980. (Box 29)
    Items include get-well letters, letters of congratulations, letters requesting help, letters of sympathy, the funeral of E. Blackburn Moore, the Advisory Committee of the Medical Alumni of the University of Virginia, Dave Satterfield's retirement from Congress and correspondence with Harry F. Byrd, Jr., and Carter O. Lowance.
  - Political Papers, 1980-1981. (Box 29)
    Items include material from or about the National Conservative Political Action Committee; Richard J. Davis (lieutenant-governor); Gerald L. Baliles; Wyatt B. Durrette, Jr.; Charles S. Robb; the 1981 election for General Assembly; the 1981 gubernatorial election (Robb v. Coleman); Sidney S. Kellam; Bill Dudley; John W. Williams, III; Martin Luther King holiday in Virginia; John Warner, concerning federal judgeship nominations; Elmon T. Gray; J. Marshall Coleman; Kit Bond (Missouri governor); pari-mutuel wagering; John N. Dalton, concerning commission appointments; and the Virginia Community College System.
  - Completed Engagements, 1980. (Box 29)
  - Personal Papers, 1980. (Box 29)
    Items include material from or about Charles Robb, the naming of the life science building at ODU for Godwin, the Eastern Virginia Medical School, Harry F. Byrd, Jr., the University of Virginia Medical Alumni Advisory Committee, Godwin's stamp and coin collecting hobby, the House Joint Resolution No. 24 signed by A.L. Philpott and Charles Robb, and a letter listing boards of corporations on which Godwin was serving.
  - General Papers, 1981. (Box 29)
    Items include material from or about letters of sympathy, congratulations on retirement, get-well letters, Albertis Harrison, the death of Colgate Darden, Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Paul Trible, and Carter O. Lowance.
  - Materials concerning Marshall Coleman, 1981. (Box 29)
    Items include the gubernatorial election of 1981 (Robb v. Coleman) and Godwin's late endorsement of Coleman.
  - Recommendations, 1981. (Box 29)
  - General Papers, 1982. (Box 30)
  - Political Papers, 1982-1983. (Box 30)
    Items concern Warner's support of Martin Luther King holiday bill; and correspondence concerning Paul Trible, the administration of Charles Robb, J. Marshall Coleman, the General Assembly and local elections of 1982-1983, D. French Slaughter, J. Kenneth Robinson's retirement from Congress, Congressman Robert Daniel, Congressman Owen B. Pickett, and Congressman Herbert H. Bateman.
  - Republican Party Papers, 1982-1983. (Box 30)
    Items include material from or about John W. Warner, the General Assembly election of 1983, Stan Parris, Robert Daniel (Congressman), the Senate race of 1982 (possibility of Byrd re-entering race, Davis v. Trible), the campaign of Melvin Spence for re-election to House of Delegates, Martin Luther King federal holiday, George Bush, and the law school at George Mason University.
  - Completed Engagements, 1982. (Box 30)
  - Invitations Declined, 1982. (Box 30)
  - Personal Papers, 1982. (Box 30)
    Items include material about or concerning Carter O. Lowance.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1982-1984 (Box 30)
    Some, not all, of the clippings directly concern Godwin. Items include material on the U. S. senatorial campaign of 1982, campaigning for Trible.
  - General Papers, 1983. (Box 30)
    Items include thank you notes, congratulatory letters, and sympathy letters; as well as correspondence from Carter O. Lowance, and Gordon Davies, Council on Higher Education concerning the Virginia Community College System.
  - Recommendations, 1983. (Box 30)
  - University of Richmond, 1983. (Box 30)
    Items include material on Godwin's service on the Board of Associates of University of Richmond.
  Series 11: Accession 1989.29
- Accession 1989.29, 1978-1990., 4 boxes. (Box 1-4)
  This addition covers committees and organizations that Mills E. Godwin belonged to and/or had an vested interest in from 1978 to 1900. These include the Obenshain Senatorial (Republican primary) Campaign of 1978, the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation, the Virginia Science Museum, the City of Suffolk, the Virginia Foundation for Independent Colleges, the Republican Party politics, Virginians for Reagan, the John N. Dalton Oncology Clinic, the Medical College of Virginia, the Virginia Wesleyan College and Godwin's opposition to pledge bond amendments to Virginia Constitution for transportation.
  Correspondents include Harry F. Byrd, Jr., Paul Trible, Wyatt Durrette, and D. French Slaughter.
  This series is arranged primarily by date.
  - Dissertation: "The role of the Governor in the Legislative Process: A Comparative Study of the Governor of Maryland and the Governor of Virginia," August 1968. (Box-folder 1:1-6)
  - Obenshain Senatorial Campaign, 1978. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Warner Senatorial Campaign, 1978. (Box-folder 1:8-9)
  - Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation, 1978-1990. (Box-folder 1:10-11)
  - Completed Engagements, 1979. (Box-folder 1:12-15)
  - Virginia Science Museum, 1979-1989. (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Bridgewater College, 1980-1982. (Box-folder 1:17-18)
  - City of Suffolk, 1980-1984. (Box-folder 1:19-20)
  - Virginia Military Institute Distinguished Lecture Series, 1980-1984. (Box-folder 1:21-22)
  - Completed Engagements, 1981. (Box-folder 1:23-25)
  - Virginia Foundation for Independent Colleges, 1982-1985. (Box-folder 1:26-27)
  - Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1982. (Box-folder 1:28-29)
  - Recommendations, 1982. (Box-folder 1:30-31)
  - Paul Trible - Senate, 1982. (Box-folder 1:32-33)
  - Engagements Completed, 1983. (Box-folder 1:34-35)
  - Invitations Declined, 1983. (Box-folder 1:36-37)
  - Mills E. Godwin - Personal Papers, 1983-1984. (Box-folder 1:38-39)
  - Imperial Briquet Corporation, 1983-1990. (Box-folder 2:1-2)
  - Suffolk Adventure Committee, 1974-1985. (Box-folder 2:3-5)
  - General Papers, 1984. (Box-folder 2:6-8)
  - Engagements - Completed, 1984. (Box-folder 2:9-11)
  - Invitations Declined, 1984. (Box-folder 2:12-13)
  - Recommendations, 1984. (Box-folder 2:14-15)
  - Republican Party, 1984. (Box-folder 2:16-18)
  - Virginians for Reagan, 1984. (Box-folder 2:19-21)
  - Harry F. Byrd, Jr., 1984-1985. (Box-folder 2:22)
  - Virginia Community College System, 1984-1988. (Box-folder 2:23-25)
  - Virginia Thanksgiving Festival, Inc., 1984-1988. (Box-folder 2:26)
  - Engagements Completed, 1985. (Box-folder 2:27-29)
  - Invitations Declined, 1985. (Box-folder 2:30-31)
  - Wyatt Durrette, 1985. (Box-folder 2:32-38)
  - Nabisco Brands, 1985. (Box-folder 3:1-4)
  - Recommendations, 1985. (Box-folder 3:5-7)
  - Republican Party, 1985. (Box-folder 3:8-9)
  - Future of Hampton Roads, 1985-1990. (Box-folder 3:10-11)
  - Political Papers, 1985-1986. (Box-folder 3:12-13)
  - Virginia Wesleyan College, 1985-1988. (Box-folder 3:14-16)
  - Completed Engagements, 1986. (Box-folder 3:17-19)
  - Invitations Declined, 1986. (Box-folder 3:20-21)
  - Recommendations, 1986. (Box-folder 3:22-23)
  - The Suffolk Adventure, 1986. (Box-folder 3:24)
  - John N. Dalton Oncology Clinic, Medical College of Virginia, 1986-1988. (Box-folder 3:25-26)
  - Dan River, 1986-1987. (Box-folder 3:27-29)
  - Republican Party, 1986-1987. (Box-folder 3:30-31)
  - Carter O. Lowance Fellowship, William and Mary Law School, 1986-1990. (Box-folder 3:32-34)
  - City of Suffolk, 1986-1990. (Box-folder 3:35-36)
  - American Electric Power Company, 1987. (Box-folder 3:37-38)
  - Completed Engagements, 1987. (Box-folder 3:39-41)
  - Invitations Declined, 1987. (Box-folder 4:1-2)
  - Recommendations, 1987. (Box-folder 4:3-5)
  - Dan River, 1987-1988. (Box-folder 4:6-7)
  - Mills E. Godwin, Jr. - UVA, Law School, Class of '38 Reunion, 1988. (Box-folder 4:8-9)
  - Recommendations, 1988. (Box-folder 4:10-13)
  - Camp Foundation, 1987-1988. (Box-folder 4:14-16)
  - Invitations Declined, 1988. (Box-folder 4:17-19)
  - Republican Party, 1988. (Box-folder 4:20-21)
  - Christmas Gifts, 1988-1989. (Box-folder 4:22-23)
  - Political Papers, 1985-1988. (Box-folder 4:24-25)
  - Beazley Foundation, 1989-1990. (Box-folder 4:26-29)
  - Camp Foundation, 1989-1990. (Box-folder 4:30-31)
  - John N. Dalton Oncology Clinic, Medical College of Virginia, 1989-1990. (Box-folder 4:32)
  - Historic St. Luke's Restoration, 1989-1990. (Box-folder 4:33)
  - Virginia Wesleyan College, 1989-1990. (Box-folder 4:34-35)
  - Engagements Completed, 1990. (Box-folder 4:36)
  - Invitations Declined, 1990. (Box-folder 4:37-38)
  - Dan River, Inc., 1990. (Box-folder 4:39)
  - D. French Slaughter, 1990. (Box-folder 4:40)
  - Pledge Bonds, 1990. (Box-folder 4:41-42)
    Smith, Byrd, Godwin, amendment to Virginia Constitution to issue local and state pledge bonds for transportation purposes.
  - Recommendations, 1990. (Box-folder 4:43-45)
  - Republican Party, 1990. (Box-folder 4:46-47)
  - Campaign Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings, May 1972-March 1973.
  - Campaign Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings, April-November 1973.
  Series 12: Accession 1994.66
- Accession 1994.66, 1981-1992., ca. 2,070 items. (Box 1-4)
  These papers composite a largely non-political nature. Most of the letters concern personal matters, invitations, get-well wishes, and letters of sympathy. Political papers concern the 1992 Virginia Bond issue, Godwin's contribution to Bush's 1988 and 1992 presidential campaigns, Chichester for lieutenant-governor in 1985, the 1989 gubernatorial race (Coleman v. Wilder), the Virginia Republican Party, Godwin's support for Trible for Republican gubernatorial candidate in 1989, the 1978-1979 HEW controversy in Virginia (desegregation of higher education), and the 1986-87 Virginia Transportation Commission.
  Correspondents include Gerald Baliles, Harry F. Byrd, Jr., J. Marshall Coleman, Albertis S. Harrison, Charles S. Robb, John Warner, Richard Short and Hunter Andrews.
  This series is arranged by subject.
  - Bond Issue 1992, 8 June 1992-21 November 1992., 34 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Items include letters to and from Mills E. Godwin about the 1992 $613 million general obligation bond issue, a report from Virginia officials arguing in favor of the bond, a copy of the report sent from state senator Hunter B. Andrews to members of the Senate, letters from the Virginians for Progress Foundation, news clippings and editorials.
  - George Bush presidential campaigns 1988 and 1992, 4 February 1988-6 November 1992, n.d., 28 items. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Items include correspondence with Godwin regarding campaign contributions, newspaper clippings, letters from representatives of the Republican Party and Bush campaign in Virginia to Godwin, and an invitation to Bush's inauguration (1988).
  - John H. Chichester, Candidate for lieutenant-governor in 1985, 17 January 1985-30 December 1985., 34 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Items include letters between Godwin and Chichester, a collection of clippings and information about Douglas Wilder's record, letters, memos, and editorials.
  - Citizens against Pledge Bonds, Inc., 2 October 1990-10 January 1992., 34 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Items include a copy of the 1991 bill for 1991 education general obligation issue, a list of proposed projects, letters to and from the opposition group (Citizens against.. .), editorials, and legal papers.
  - J. Marshall Coleman, 13 June 1988-3 December 1989, n.d., 42 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Items include the campaign for Governor in 1988 - editorials, newspaper articles, correspondence between Coleman and Godwin, correspondence with Harry F. Byrd, Jr., an extensive Wall Street Journal article about the race, miscellaneous letters, etc.
  - College of William and Mary, 2 July 1979-27 February 1986., 27 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Items include invitations to various functions, papers concerning Camp Foundation, personal letters, correspondence between Godwin and Doug Rendleman (Godwin Professor of Law at Marshall-Wythe School of Law), letters to and from Anne Dobie Peebles, Davis Paschall and Thomas Graves, letters concerning the 1984 presidential search, news clippings and letters to and from Margaret Cook of Swem Library.
  - College of William and Mary, 21 March 1986-26 October 1989., 24 items. (Box-folder 1:7)
    Items include invitations, papers concerning the planning of the Tercentenary Celebration, news clipping of Queen Elizabeth's address commemorating the Glorious Revolution, letters to and from Paul Verkuil, Tim Sullivan, Anne Dobie Peebles, and photographs.
  - Engagements Completed, 1987-1992. (Box-folder 1:8-13)
    - Engagements Completed, 8 September 1987-20 June 1988., 14 items. (Box-folder 1:8)
      Items include thank you letters and letters of regret for functions, banquets, visitations.
    - Engagements Completed, 7 July 1988-22 November 1988., 7 items. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Items include thank you letters and letters of regret for parties, receptions, etc.
    - Engagements Completed, 30 March 1989-9 November 1989., 10 items. (Box-folder 1:10)
      Items include thank you letters and letters of regret concerning various banquets, parties, and gatherings.
    - Engagements Completed, 3 December 1990-16 October 1991., 22 items. (Box-folder 1:11)
      Items include thank you letters and letters of regret to various people and organizations.
    - Engagements Completed, 16 October 1991-17 November 1991., 40 items. (Box-folder 1:12)
      Items include correspondence with Oliver North and paper from the International Churchill Society (including a letter to Justice Clarence Thomas), letters to and from Godwin about the 1991 International Churchill Society Conference in Richmond, Virginia and copies of a speech and essay by Churchill).
    - Engagements Completed, 28 January 1992-30 December 1992., 27 items. (Box-folder 1:13)
      Items include correspondence between Godwin and Tim Sullivan concerning Sullivan's inauguration as president of the College of William and Mary, letters concerning speaking engagements at Paul D. Camp Community College, Diane Russell's fourth grade class at Larchmont Elementary School, the State Council on Higher Education and letters concerning other engagements.
  - Elon College, 12 April 1983-21 December 1989., 29 items. (Box-folder 1:14)
    Items include papers, business letters and personal letters concerning affairs at Elon College in North Carolina.
  - J. Smith Ferebee - In Memoriam, 5 September 1985-24 April 1990., 15 items. (Box-folder 1:15)
    Items include letters, a copy of the eulogy given by Godwin, and news clippings.
  - General Papers and Letters, 1981-1992. (Box 1-2)
    - General Papers and Letters, 27 August 1981-8 April 1985., 44 items. (Box-folder 1:16)
      Items include personal letters, letters to and from William B. Spong, former Dean of the Marshall-Wythe Law School, and information about Festival Williamsburg.
    - General Papers and Letters, 9 April 1985-19 December 1985., 55 items. (Box-folder 1:17)
      Items include personal letters.
    - General Papers and Letters, 30 December 1985-13 March 1986, 33 items. (Box-folder 1:18)
      Items include personal letters from Charles S. Robb, John Dalton and other friends and acquaintances.
    - General papers and letters, 6 June 1986-31 December 1986., 38 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
    - General papers and letters, 7 January 1987-22 July 1987., 40 items. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Items include personal letters, and letters and papers concerning Godwin's involvement in various organizations and enterprises.
    - General papers and letters, 6 August 1987-31 December 1987., 35 items. (Box-folder 2:3)
    - General papers and letters, 4 January 1988-15 May 1988., 31 items. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Items include personal letters concerning personal commitments (e.g., Bridgewater College, Medical College of Virginia, Boy Scouts).
    - General papers and letters, 1 June 1988-15 December 1988., 33 items. (Box-folder 2:5)